<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons viz. I. The diseases that make a stoppage to Englands mercies discovered and attended with their remedies : in a sermon delivered at Margaretson Fish-street-hill, London : II. A preperation for suffering in these plundering times / by William Bridge ...</title>
            <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
            <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12156234</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12156234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55139</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55139)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 243:E91, no 37, 243:E91, no 38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons viz. I. The diseases that make a stoppage to Englands mercies discovered and attended with their remedies : in a sermon delivered at Margaretson Fish-street-hill, London : II. A preperation for suffering in these plundering times / by William Bridge ...</title>
                  <title>Sermons. Selections</title>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
                  <author>I. A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p., [1], 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Allen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Address "To the reader" signed: I.A.</note>
                  <note>Second sermon separated in filmed copy has separate t.p. with title A sermon containing some comfortable directions for svch as have been or may be driven from their houses, goods or country.</note>
                  <note>Second sermon has separate Wing number.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Lamentations --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Faith --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55139:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TVVO SERMONS: VIZ.</p>
            <p>I. The Diſeaſes that make a ſtoppage to ENGLANDS Mercies diſcovered, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with their remedies. IN A Sermon delivered at <hi>Margarets</hi> on Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet-hill, <hi>LONDON:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM BRIDGE,</hi> Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thy deſtruction is of thy ſelf, but thy ſalvation is of me.</l>
               <l>Except ye Repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh,</l>
               <bibl>LUKE 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>II. A preparation for ſuffering in theſe Plundering Times.</p>
            <p>IT is Ordered by the Committee of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament, concerning Printing, that this Book be printed. John White.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for BENJAMIN ALLEN, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes-head Alley. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:55139:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55139:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is Gods wont to warn before he ſmite a people, thereby walking himſelf after his own rule, <hi>Deut. 20.10, 13.</hi> who would have no City to be deſtroyed till peace hath firſt been offered to it; the ſword of the Lord is ever drawn, his bow bent, his arows prepared, his inſtruments of death made ready, his cup mingled, yet he doth not uſe to powre down his plagues, untill he have rained a ſhowre of mercie before them, he doth not ſurpriſe men at unawares, God never diſcharges his murthering peeces, till he have firſt diſcharged his warning ones, <hi>pax domini</hi> Luke <hi>10.</hi> peace to this houſe was ſounded at every doore where the Apoſtles came. All Ages and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will bear witneſſe to this truth, the old world, <hi>Sodom, Pharaoh,</hi> &amp;c. but no Nation or Age can better ſubſcribe to Gods goodneſſe, and fair dealing in this then we, who have been warned ſometimes by prodigious ſignes, as by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of that wonderfull Comet <hi>An. 1618.</hi> as importing ſome ſtrange changes which we have ſeen and heard ſince, and as if its laſt influence might ſeem to end in this Iſland, vvhen it blazed over <hi>England,</hi> it was ſeen no more, And <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licius Stargardenſis</hi> (a noted Astrologer) held, that its influence was like to continue between twenty and thirty years: ſometimes by his Miniſters, by his adminiſtration of Juſtice, and dealing with other Nations; how long hath the ſword walked circuit in <hi>Germany,</hi> and in <hi>Ireland?</hi> ſometimes by leſſer and lighter judgements; how long hath the plague continued in this Citie without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion? ſometime by taking many godly out of the world, and the removing many others out of the Kingdom, who were wont to ſtand in the gap; ſometime by a generall withdrawing himſelf, pulling down his hangings, not aſſiſting his ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And unleſſe we will wilfully ſhut our eyes, how hath the goodneſſe, patience, bounty, mercifull, and powerfull dealings of God towards us, and for us of late, been as an hand put forth to leade us home unto him? to cauſe us to meet him, and take warning that we might prevent theſe wasting calamities that are gathered together in a black cloud, as though they meant to empty themſelves in a ſhowre of blood upon our heads? But we are ſo far from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king warning, that we ſtudy to haſten our own ruine, almoſt every one inſtead of bringing his bucket of water to quench the fire that is already flaming about our ears, bring their bellowes in their hands to blow up theſe coals of diſſention in all places, ſo that now not onely is there a Kingdome divided, but the head and the members divided, and the members among themſelves, Cities and Townes divided, yea families divided, Parents againſt children, brother againſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and familiar friends become bitter enemies one to another, the moſt ſure ſymptome and preſage of a fearfull deſolation to fall upon all, unleſſe ſome ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die remedy be applyed to this deſperate diſeaſe, and the great God himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our Phiſitian and heale our diſtempers. I ſhall deſire to commend theſe two Sermons to thy ſexious conſideration; in the one thou ſhalt ſee there is a ſtoppage
<pb facs="tcp:55139:3"/>made of Gods mercies (who was coming to heal us but we would not be healed) the cauſes are diſcovered, and the remedies preſcribed, that could we ſo go to work to open theſe ſtoppings, and bring God again into the way of his mercies; could we ſee our ſins removed, and God returned, I might then truly ſay that there would be yet hope for <hi>England.</hi> The other Sermon is a preparative to bear that croſſe that ſo many have already on their backs, <hi>viz.</hi> of being turned out of all our earthly comforts; a ſad calamity indeed, but now too uſuall, and when ſo many of our neighbours houſes are on fire, why ſhould we think to eſcape ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, that are as deep in ſin as they? being therefore forewarn'd, let us be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and get into God and his favor, as that one neceſſary thing for us all to look after, as the onely means to keepe us from ſinking under the waves that flow in upon all, eſpecially on Gods people; experience ſhewing, that if we vvill live in the power of godlineſſe, and not walk in the ſame exceſſe of riot with the world, we ſhall make our ſelves a prey, and had need to have our helmets on to latch the blowes that fall upon us, and reſolve to ſit looſe from the world, that we may ſuffer the ſpoyling of our goods with joy, and be able to ſay with that noble Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; who being told of the death of his children, Anſwered; I know well they were all begot mortall. 2. That his goods were confiſcate, I knew what was but for mine uſe, was not mine. 3. That his honor was gone, I knew no glory could be everlaſting on this miſerable earth. 4. That his ſentence was to dye, that is nothing, Nature hath given the like ſentence both of my condemners and of me; Now ſhould we get a ſtocke of faith and learn how to uſe it, to live by it when our lands, our ſtocks, our trades, our friends, our wit, our ſhifts (as the ordinary means of our livelihood) ſhall faile us. That we may live not onely above our fears, and troubles, and doubts, but above the world, above our ſelves, in God and in Chriſt, in whom vve may ſee ſupply to all our vvants, ſatisfaction to all our deſires, and have recompenſe for all our loſſes, and every thing that may make for our good and welfare; light in our darkneſſe, life in our death, ſtrength in our weakneſſe, riches in our poverty, and comfort our ſelves, that we ſerve a Maſter that will one day right all our wrongs, reckoning the injuries that be done to his, as done to himſelfe; ſo that we ſhould not think much to part with our Country, our Children, our Poſſeſſions, our life if the world will take them from us, for Chriſt and his Goſpels ſake. All theſe, and much better than theſe ſhall be reſtored to us one day, and vve may ſay thus to our ſelves; yet I am not miſerable ſo long as my Redeemer is happy, he lives, and I ſhall live vvith him, men may take from me my goods, but they cannot rob me of my grace, they may baniſh me from my Countrey, but not from Heaven, take from me my life, but not my happines; no, my faith, my heaven, my ſoul, my happines is in his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that will ſafely preſerve them for me, and me for them. But <hi>I</hi> fear I have held thee too long in the porch, I ſhall now open thee the door and let thee in, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God to make thoſe leſſons as profitable to thee, as the Authors deſire vvas they might both in his preaching them, and his vvillingneſſe to have them publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for publike good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55139:3"/>
            <head>The Diſeaſes that make a ſtoppage to <hi>Englands</hi> Mercies diſcovered; and attended with their remedies. Delivered in a SERMON at <hi>Margarets</hi> on Fiſhſtreet-hill, <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JOSH. 7.4.</bibl>
                  <p>So there went up thither of the people about three thouſand men, and they fled before the men of Ai.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Chapter you have a Treatiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Achans</hi> ſin, branching it ſelf into three parts, one concerning the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſin, the ſecond concerning the diſcovery of it, and the third concerning the puniſhment thereof. As for the ſin it ſelf, the commiſſion thereof, what it was, you read in the firſt verſe, that the children of Iſrael had committed a treſpaſſe; God had commanded that all the ſpoil of <hi>Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> ſhould be conſecrated unto himſelf, and that the firſt fruits of all ſhould be his; <hi>Jericho</hi> being the firſt City that they took in, in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> by right it did belong unto God, all the treaſure, ſilver and gold, wealth and goods that was therein, properly it did belong unto God; now <hi>Achan</hi> be playes the thief, and does appropriate ſome of Gods goods, and wealth unto himſelf; this was charged upon him as a ſin, and ſo upon all Iſrael, as at the firſt verſe; keeping from God any thing that does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto him, is a ſin. Now in the ſecond place this ſin
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55139:4"/>was diſcovered by occaſion of the defeat that was before the town of <hi>Ai;</hi> they paſſing on from <hi>Jericho</hi> (at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe) unto the town of <hi>Ai,</hi> they laid ſiege to it; but their ſiege was broken up, and three thouſand men fled, and thirty ſix men were ſlain, verſe 4, 5. Sins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in one City, will follow us unto another, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertake us there. Oh what unexpected wayes and means hath God for to bring out mens ſin to light? Three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men flee before the men of <hi>Ai,</hi> and thirty ſix men are ſlain, and this was made the means of diſcovery of <hi>Achans</hi> ſin, who would have thought that there ſhould have been ſuch a diſcovery as this?</p>
            <p>The work was hindred by this defeat, and that ſets them on work to ſearch out the cauſe; and ſhews,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That afflictions ſhould ſet us on work, to ſearch out our ſins, and the cauſe of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſins ſhall not alway be pocketed up, but ſhall be diſcovered, though never ſo ſecret.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That God hath ſtrange wayes to diſcover mans ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>
               </label> But why muſt the children of Iſrael be beaten here by the men of <hi>Ai?</hi> and why muſt one mans ſin be puniſhed upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all? ſurely the children of Iſrael were in covenant one with another, and ſo being in covenant together, the ſin of the one not being puniſhed by the reſt, was charged upon all the reſt. As for <hi>England,</hi> either we are in covenant one with another, or elſe we are not: Either there is a nationall covenant, or elſe there is not: If there be not a Nationall covenant, as was among the Jews, why do we not rather ſay, the Churches of <hi>England</hi> then the Church? And if there be a Nationall covenant, the ſin of one is made the ſin of the reſt, what ſins do we bring upon our ſelves? But they muſt flee before the men of <hi>Ai,</hi> why? Becauſe that the men of <hi>Ai</hi> were to be deſtroyed with a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55139:4"/>great deſtruction, therefore God does firſt ſuffer them to prevail, the more to imbitter and ſtir up the ſpirits of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el againſt them, this did provoke them.</p>
            <p>Whence I take up theſe two Obſervations: The firſt is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> Where God is in a way of mercie towards a people, there ſin makes a ſtoppage in his proceedings. The ſecond is this:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> When God intends utterly to deſtroy his enemies, he does firſt ſuffer his own ſervants, and deareſt children to flee &amp; fall before them. Concerning the firſt:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>1</label> Where God is in a way of mercie towards his people, there ſin does make a ſtoppage in his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: So here God was in a way of mercie towards his people, carrying of them into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but in the way they ſin, <hi>Achan</hi> playes the thief, mark what a ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age this made in the way of mercie; So you have it in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> 24.20. Though God be about to do you good, and have done you good, yet <hi>If you forſake the Lord, and ſerve ſtrange gods, he will turn</hi> from the good he is a doing, <hi>and do you hurt, after he hath done you good.</hi> So in <hi>Jer.</hi> 28.9. <hi>At what inſtant I ſhall</hi> ſay or <hi>ſpeak concerning a Nation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Kingdom, to build, and to plant it:</hi> that is, At what time I ſhall give ſenſible teſtimony of good to a land or nation; <hi>If it do evil in my ſight, that it obey not my voice, then I will repent of the good,</hi> &amp;c. So that ſins committed againſt God when he is in a way of mercy, do make a ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in thoſe proceedings of mercie. There are theſe two or three reaſons for it:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt of all, ſins committed when God is in a way of mercie, are a ſlighting of mercie. Amongſt your ſelves, if you be doing any ſpeciall work before others, that they may take notice of you, and they ſlight your
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55139:5"/>work, you will leave off work, and work no more: now I ſay, when as God is in a way of mercie, and you then ſin againſt him, your ſins do ſlight mercie, nay then ſayes God I wil turn away, it will make a ſtoppage in this work.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Again ſecondly, thoſe mercies that come unto Gods people, come unto them in the way of a promiſe. And Gods promiſes they are, either ſpirituall, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirituall things, or temporall, concerning temporall things. If they be ſpirituall promiſes, concerning ſpirituall things, then they are abſolute, bottomed and grounded upon no condition: as the promiſe he made, that <hi>he would drown the world no more,</hi> ſayes the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> ſuch a covenant as he made with <hi>Noah,</hi> he makes with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that runs upon no condition; he does not ſay, If the world goes on, and ſerve me, I will drown it no more: but the promiſe runs upon no condition, and ſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of grace runs upon no condition: for if it runs upon a condition of faith, God promiſes to give faith, God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes perſeverance, upon the exerciſe of grace he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to give the exerciſe of grace, all ſpirituall promiſes run upon no condition. But now outward promiſes run upon condition, and therefore if men do not keep the condition, God takes himſelf free, and will turn himſelf out of the way of his mercie. You have an expreſſion to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34. <hi>After the number of the dayes in which ye ſearched the land, even forty dayes (each day for a yeer) ſhall you bear your in quity, even forty years, and ye ſhall know my breach of promiſe.</hi> Will God break his promiſe? As much as if he ſhould have ſaid, I have promiſed to bring you into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> upon ſuch and ſuch conditions; but now, if you do not perform the condition, I count my ſelf free, and you ſhall know my breach of promiſe, that I will not give you the thing that I am about to give you.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:55139:5"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, God never gives his people any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, but he gives it them in a way of mercie. He does not think it enough to give them that which is mercie, but he will give it them in a way of mercie. As now in your gifts to God, if you be gracious, you do not think it enough to do that which is gracious, but do it in a gracious manner; ſo God in his gifts to you, will not onely give you that which is mercie, but he will give it you in a way of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: but now if God ſhould be in a way of mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his people, and they ſin againſt him, and he ſhould go on to give them the mercie, they would be hardned in their ſin, and ſo it would not come unto them in the way of mercie: Therefore, if God be in a way of mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his people, and they ſin againſt him, he will break off the courſe of his mercy, and go another way, and there ſhall be a ſtoppage made in theſe proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>But you will ſay we ſee the contrary: who have more bleſſings, and outward mercies, then the Church of</hi> Rome? <hi>who more ſinfull? what adulteries, what idolatries, ſorceries, oppoſition of Saints and Miniſters? and you know what plenty is among them, and God goes on to give them mercie after mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, outward bleſſing after outward bleſſing, and therefore this is not true, we ſee it in experience otherwiſe, that our ſins do not make a ſtoppage in the proceedings of mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> But for anſwer hereunto, The thing is not true, God does not go on in a way of bleſſing and mercie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: Beloved, of all afflictions, it is the greateſt affliction to be without affliction; of all judgements, it is the greateſt judgement to want judgement: as you may ſee for this purpoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. <hi>Why ſhould you be ſtricken any more; ye will revolt more and more:</hi> It is the greateſt ſtroke, not to be ſmitten, and the greateſt affliction to be denyed affliction, when there is uſe and need of it: now though
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55139:6"/>the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that party flouriſh in the world, yet their ſouls are ſmitten, God ſmites them with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and with ſpirituall death, ſo that there is a ſtoppage made in the proceedings of mercie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But I rather anſwer it thus: When God is in a way of mercie towards his people, towards his Church, then ſin will make a ſtoppage: Thoſe of <hi>Rome</hi> are no true Church, the Church was in <hi>Babilon,</hi> but <hi>Babilon</hi> was not the Church; the Church was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but <hi>Egypt</hi> was not the Church; <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom, Sodom</hi> was not in <hi>Lots</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; <hi>Rome</hi> is called <hi>Babilon, Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Sodom;</hi> they are not the Church of God; but if the Church of God ſin when God is in a way of mercie, a ſtoppage ſhall be made rather for them then for others, for theſe two or three Reaſons:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, they are in Gods houſe, and their ſin is greater. The great houſe of God is as a great mans houſe, who hath ſome ſervants that doth his work abroad in the field, ſome that tend in his chamber, that are neerer round about him: if thoſe ſervants that are neer him be naught, and vile, it makes more to the diſhonour of the maſter, then if thoſe were ſo that are abroad in the field: now Gods people are a people that are round about him, neer unto him, his houſhold ſervants, and therefore if they ſin when God is in a way of mercie, God will turn out of that way, and there ſhall be a ſtoppage made in Gods proceedings.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, their ſin is of all others the moſt ſcandalous, and therefore the worſe, the more diſhonor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, the more provoking. If two men be drunk, one a Profeſſor, and the other not; why there is no ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall ariſes from the drunkenneſſe of him that is no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor; but if a Profeſſor be gotten in, and made drunk,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55139:6"/>they are all ſo, what a ſcandall ariſeth? And ſo, if two commit adultery, the one a Profeſſor, and the other not, the ſcandall ariſeth from the Profeſſor; Profeſſion is the ground of Scandall. And therefore, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.12. when as <hi>Amaſa</hi> was ſlain, and laid in his blood, the people made a ſtay, and went no further, till they drew him out of the way, and caſt a cloath over him; ſo when a Profeſſor fals, and lyes in his blood, there is a ſtand made in peoples du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and converſations; and therfore juſt that there ſhould be a ſtop made in the proceedings of Gods mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, their ſins are moſt againſt the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Sins againſt the remedy, are the greateſt ſins: and therefore his ſin is greateſt, that commits adultery being marryed, then his that commits fornication, though both be evil, becauſe he ſins againſt the remedy: now the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God have more remedies againſt ſins then others, more light, more grace, more means, more helps; and therfore if they ſin when God is in a way of mercie, God will rather make a ſtoppage in them then in others. O that I might leave this impreſſion upon you that are Profeſſors, and godly, that you may take heed how you ſin againſt God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Why ſhould this be, that ſo ſmall a ſin ſhould turn the great God of heaven out of the way of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie? <hi>Achan</hi> commits but a ſmall ſin, and what a mighty ſtop is made in the way of mercie? So, <hi>David</hi> numbers the people, it was no great matter, and a plague breaks out preſently; what is the reaſon, that for ſins that are little and ſmall, ſuch a ſtoppage ſhould be made in the proceedings and mercie of the great God?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> For anſwer three things; 1. There is nothing ſmall between God and us, and it is true. If thou haſt but the leaſt crum of bread, it is a great mercie, becauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55139:7"/>it comes from the great God; and if you commit a ſin, though never ſo little in your own eyes, it is great, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe committed againſt the great God; I may boldly ſay thus much, that men ſin a great ſin, in ſaying their ſin is ſmall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, ſometimes what falls ſhort in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſin, is made up in the number of ſin: Great ſins do go alone, ſmaller ſins do go by companies: as with creatures, ſo with ſins; you ſhall obſerve it ſo in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and in the air, and in the water, and in the earth: In the heavens, but one great Sun, many leſſe Stars; In the air, you have but few great and kingly birds, the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle ſhe flyes alone, but your Pigeons that are leſſer, flye by flights; In the water, your great Whale goes alone, but your leſſer Herring go by ſholes; On the earth, the great Elephant goes alone, your leſſer ſheep go by flocks, and your Hogs by herds; the leſſer Sands infinite in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Rocks fewer: And ſo with mens ſins; great ſins they go alone, but leſſer ſins go by companies, and oftentimes the number of your leſſer ſins do make up what is wanting in the greatneſſe of your ſin. A man may be drunk but once or twice in his life, in the groſſe act of it, but he may be ſo often in drunken company, and ſpend away ſo many hours which ſhall amount to drunkenneſs; a man may commit adultery but once in his life, but he may have as many unclean thoughts, as ſhall amount to adultery: So, that what fals ſhort in the greatneſſe of ſin, is made up in the number; and therefore ſay not, why ſhould God for a little ſin turn out of the way of mercie? it may be the number of your little ſins amount to the greateſt ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Beloved, God will make good his Name to the utmoſt, and his name is, <hi>A Jealous God;</hi> now a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55139:7"/>husbands jealouſie ariſech not, when he ſees his wife commit adultery, but if he do but ſee her playing and ſporting with a ſtranger; ſo Gods jealouſie ariſeth, not onely when we commit the groſſe act of Idolatry, when we bow before an Idoll, but if we be ſporting and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Superſtition; for God is a jealous God: And though the husband do not ſee cauſe enough to turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wife, becauſe of her ſporting and playing, and dallying, he may ſee cauſe enough to deny ſuch a courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; ſo God, though he does not give a Bill of Divorce for ſuch a ſin which you count leſſer, yet he may ſee cauſe enough to make a ſtoppage in his proceedings of mercie. Thus the Doctrine ſtands firm, when God is in a way of mercie towards his people, if they do ſin againſt him, their ſins may make a ſtoppage in his proceedings. By way of Application;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Hence you may ſee what the reaſon is, why there is a ſtop made now of late in our <hi>England</hi> mercies. This laſt yeer God hath done great things for <hi>England,</hi> as ever <hi>England</hi> ſaw, and that man that ſees it not, I ſhall think that Scripture hath taken hold upon him, which you have in <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.5, 6. <hi>Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arm, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord, for he ſhall be like the heath in the deſart, and ſhall not ſee when good cometh,</hi> whether out of envie or malice, but when good comes upon a people, he ſhall not ſee it: but who doth not ſee, what a black cloud is drawn over us again? When the waters ſwell and ſtand up, you ſay ſurely there is a ſtop made; the waters do not run down as before, not long ſince Juſtice and Judgement did run down like a mighty ſtream; but now, how the waters ſwell, gather, and ſtand up again? wicked men lye in priſon, and thoſe not cenſured: Prieſts and Jeſuits lye condemned, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55139:8"/>choſe not executed: the Plague is begun, and that is not quenched: The Sword hath begun to drink deep in our Brethrens blood, and that is not ſheathed: The wrath of our King is enkindled: Divers of our Parliamentary Worthies accuſed of high Treaſon: certainly there is a ſtoppage made in the proceedings of <hi>Englands</hi> mercies; oh Beloved, this our ſin hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But you will ſay unto me, Shall there be a ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page made for ever in the mercies of <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> You will finde (for anſwer) if you look into Scripture, that there is a two-fold ſtoppage of mercie: Finall, and Preſent: Finall, as God was in a way of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie towards <hi>Saul,</hi> and was about to ſettle the kingdom upon him and his poſterity for ever; but he ſinned, and the Lord turned away from <hi>Saul,</hi> and turned away from him for ever, there was a finall ſtoppage of mercie made. Now though there be a ſtop made in the way of Gods mercie towards <hi>England,</hi> I conceive there is not a finall ſtoppage. And my Reaſons are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe that though many difficulties and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains do ariſe, yet we ſee how one after another they do melt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And becauſe God hath raiſed up inſtrements that are unwearyed in his ſervice, working night and day, and are unwearyed in the work of the Lord.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As alſo becauſe that the type of this work does ſpeak as much. The children of Iſraels coming out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and building the Temple, is a type of our coming out of Antichriſtian bondage, and the great Reformation that is now begun: Now then though there were many lets and hindrances by <hi>Tobiah,</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi> and others, they could never hinder it fully, but it recovered its ſelf,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55139:8"/>and was driven on: ſo in this building and worke of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, though the <hi>Tobiahs</hi> and <hi>Sanballats</hi> of the times may cauſe the work to ceaſe for a time, the building ſhall get up, and ſhall not fully ceaſe, but the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſhall be driven on in the deſpight of all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Therefore it is not a finall ſtop now made in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> mercies. But there is a preſent ſtop, as when the plague broke out in <hi>Davids</hi> time; and ſuch a ſtoppage is made now.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But what evill and hurt is in this, if a finall ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page be not made?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Is it nothing in your ears, and in your hearts, that the Lord ſhould turn out of a way of mercy? you read in the 2 <hi>Judg.</hi> when the Angel came with a meſſage unto the people, and told them that the Canaanites ſhould be as <hi>thorns in their ſides,</hi> and <hi>a ſnare unto them, they lift up their voice and wept, and they called the name of the place Bochim:</hi> you ſhall be brought into Canaan the promiſed land, but the natives ſhall be ſo mixt amongſt you, as they ſhall be thorns in your ſides, hereupon they lift up their voice and wept: and ſo though the work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation be carried on, the <hi>Canaanites</hi> may be left to be as thorns in your ſides, until Chriſt come. Oh that we could lift up our voice and weep, that the place might be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Bochim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. When God breaks off the way of his mercy, then his wrath breaks out; he does not turn out of the way of his mercy, but he turns into the way of his judgement. Why to a loving childe this is a very cutting word, your father is angry with you. I may ſpeak this to you, there is a ſtop made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, and your father is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, this is much.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If there be a ſtoppage made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55139:9"/>though but preſent, there is an obſtruction in all your comforts: you are ſenſible of the obſtructions of your body, will you not be ſenſible of State obſtructions, of Church obſtructions? Suppoſe you were in <hi>Ireland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>girt with the enemy, and were in danger to have your convoy cut off, that ſhould bring you victuall and ſupply, would it not make you feare? Beloved, we have beene begirt with enemies a long time, and God hath raiſed us up a convoy to bring us victuall; we do not know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our convoy ſhall be taken away, though but for the preſent. Certainly there is a theife in our candle that does make our comforts ſmeare out.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But what is that theife in our candle? it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent to us all there is a ſtop made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, what are thoſe ſins (for it is a day of humiliation) that have made a ſtoppage in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> This is that I ſpecially aime at, that you may ſee what you are to be humbled for this day and others. Paralell our condition with others in Scripture, and we ſhall finde ſix or ſeven things eſpecially, that do make a ſtoppage in mercy coming to a people, and you ſhall find them in our land.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An unwillingneſſe and backwardneſſe to the great work of Reformation, to the great work that God is now about, is one thing that doth make a ſtoppage in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Englands</hi> mercy. When the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they groaned unto the Lord, God ſent a deliverer to them, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and they being vext by their taskmaſters, after he came they murmured, and for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhof ſoul, hearkned not unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> God bare with that, till he got them on the other ſide of the water, carried them through the red ſea, when they came there, tho they did ſin and murmure, God did not ſwear they ſhould not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55139:9"/>enter into Canaan, but at the laſt they made them a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and they would return back to Egypt, ſayes God, ſeeing you are there, I ſwear in my wrath you ſhall never enter into my reſt, but your carcaſes ſhall fall here; you ſhall neither go backward nor forward; We have a long time, the Lord look upon us, ſet under Egyptian dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the Lord hath ſent his Meſſengers to you to draw you out, and you would not, or for anguiſh of ſoul you hearkned not; Well, but now there is a tender of Reformation made, and hath been lately: if people ſhall ſay now, What need this Reformation? Were not things well before? This provokes the Lord, and cauſes him to ſay, Your carcaſes ſhall fall. And yet, Oh how hath this been among us, what ado is here ſayes one? What need this work? Were not things well before? 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.32. <hi>In thoſe dayes the Lord began to cut Iſrael ſhort,</hi> What dayes were thoſe? They were in a way of Reformation, and they cut ſhort the Reformation; and in thoſe dayes the Lord began to cut them ſhort of mercie. At the 18. verſe, he got together the Worſhippers of <hi>Baal</hi> by craft; at the 25. verſe, he ſlayes them; at the 29. they break down the Images in the houſe of <hi>Baal:</hi> Howbeit at the 29. verſe, <hi>From the ſins of Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat who made Iſrael to ſin, Jehu departed not, &amp;c.</hi> Then at the 32. verſe, when they thus cut ſhort Reformation, the Lord began to cut them ſhort. You know what our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt ſayes, <hi>Oh Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often would I have gathered you, and you would not; behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> Beloved, when Chriſt comes to gather us, as certainly there is a time when Chriſt comes a gathering, and if peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will not be gathered, then behold thy houſe is left deſolate. God hath made a tender of Reformation
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55139:10"/>lately among you, this is one ſin that hath made a ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page in the proceedings of your mercy, people have been backward and unwilling unto this great worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A tempting of God does alſo ſtop and hinder the proceeding of mercy. They tempted the Lord, and the Lords mercy was ſtopped.</p>
            <p>You finde in Scripture, people are ſaid to tempt God; 1. either when they doubt of Gods preſence, after God hath eſpecially appeared to them: <hi>they tempted God, and ſayd, is God amongſt us?</hi> after God had appeared to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again, when a man does not rely, and live upon Gods All-ſufficiency, when God hath appeared in that way. It is ſayd of the Iſraelites <hi>they tempted God,</hi> and ſayd, <hi>can God provide a table in the wilderneſſe?</hi> As <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> obſerves well, the Iſraelites were not ſo ſilly, as to think God was not able; they knew God opened the rock, and brought them through the red-ſea, but this was the language of their converſation, <hi>can God provide a table in the Wilderneſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A man is ſaid to tempt God, when as he does tye and limit God unto ordinary means, when God is in an extraordinory way. And ſo it is ſaid of <hi>AhaꝪ</hi> that he tempted God, and would not take a ſigne; what is the meaning of that? that is, that he would go in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way; <hi>why</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſhould I tempt God,</hi> and <hi>require a ſigne,</hi> and go in an extraordinary way? I will go in an ordinary way: when as God is in an extraordinary way of mercy towards his people, to tye God to ordinary means, is a tempting of God. Now I appeal to you, whether or no, we have not tempted God, God hath appeared gloriouſly, oh yet we have ſayd is God among
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55139:10"/>us? how few live upon Gods All-ſufficiencie, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he hath appeared ſo gloriouſly? and we ſee no way and means for ſuch a Reformation as is ſpoken of, tying and limiting of God unto an ordinary way, when God is working extraordinarily. This is a ſecond ſinne that hath made a ſtoppage in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, this temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Abuſing of Gods inſtruments which he raiſeth up for to do his worke by, doth exceedingly provoke, and makes a ſtoppage in the mercy of God. There are two wayes whereby his inſtruments are abuſed; either idoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and deifying of them, or wronging, ſcorning, and jearing of them, falfly accuſing and condemning of them. The firſt way the Jews ſinned, when they cryed <hi>the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord,</hi> and deifyed that; well ſayes Chriſt, <hi>there ſhall not be one ſtone left upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi> God raiſed up the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> people idolized him, he was taken away, and a ſtoppage was made in that way of mercy: on the other ſide ſcouning and evill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the inſtruments of Reformation, and falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them that God does ſet up, this makes a ſtoppage in mercy, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12. <hi>Moſes</hi> was appointed by God to bring them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> marke how they ſpeake againſt him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>And they ſaid hath the Lord indeed ſpoken only by</hi> Moſes? <hi>hath he not alſo ſpoken by us?</hi> ſhe what follows 9.10. ver. <hi>And the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt them, and he departed. And the cloud drparted from off the Tabernacle, and behold</hi> Miriam <hi>became leprous, &amp;c.</hi> marke what a ſtop is made, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. Miriam <hi>was ſhut out of the Camp ſeven dayes, and the people journied not,</hi> only becauſe they opened their mouthes againſt this inſtrument of Go that was employd in this worke. So <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Kerah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Ahiram</hi> riſe up againſt <hi>Moſex</hi> and <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55139:11"/>inſtruments that God employed in his ſervice, you may ſee what became of it in the following part of the Chapter, the Lord would have conſumed the whole Congregation, <hi>And Moſes ſayd to Aaron, take a Cenſer, and put fire therein from off the Altar, and put on incenſe, and go quickly unto the Congregation, and make an atonement for them, for there is wrath gone out from the Lord. verſ.</hi> 45.46. Oh my beloved, I would to God we were not guilty here; the Lord hath raiſed up a bleſſed and happy Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and hath made them inſtruments of much good unto this Kingdome; ſome idolize and deiſie them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers again have accuſed them as traitors, the great Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Judges of our Kingdome, no leſſe than traitors: thus have the Inſtruments of the Lord been abuſed, and how can this but make a ſtoppage in our mercy?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> What is this to us? we have not accuſed them, that is done above.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I pray do but conſider the place diligently, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. it is ſayd <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and two hundred and fifty Princes, men of renown, roſe up againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> but wrath breaks out upon the whole Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Lord would have conſumed them all, why? becauſe they were not humbled. And if upon all this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill that hath been done to the inſtruments of God, we have not been humbled, the wrath of God may breake out upon us all, and juſtly it ſhould be, that a ſtop ſhould be made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Carrying on the worke of Reformation, and the great affairs of the Church, upon the ſhoulders of humane prudence, will make a ſtoppage in the way of mercy. You know that when <hi>David</hi> broughr back the Ark, they were very cheerfull, and went along withall, nothing fearing, at laſt <hi>Uzza</hi> layes his hand upon the Ark, and is ſmitten,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55139:11"/>a cloud ariſeth, <hi>David</hi> is diſmayed, a ſtop is made in the buſineſſe, what is the matter? the Text tells us, they carried the Arke upon the Cart, and it ſhould have been carried upon mens ſhoulders. So when God is bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back the Arke, men ſet it upon a Cart, and upon the ſhoulder of humane wiſedome; oh ſayes one, there is no government appointed in the Church, it is a matter of humane prudence, and ſo will you cart the Ark of God? look that God will make a ſtoppage in mercy. And this is another ſin that provokes God to make a ſtoppage in our <hi>Englands</hi> mercy.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the fift place. As prayer and humiliation does exceedingly further the worke of God in the hands of his people; ſo the falling and ſlacking of the hands in thoſe two works, doth make a ſtop in mercy, and hath done in our mercy. In the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23. we read there, that good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> went a great way in the worke of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Law is brought out, his heart trembles, the images are pulled down, he executes juſtice upon <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts; yet notwithſtanding all he had done, <hi>the Lord turned not from the fierceneſſe of his wrath, wherewith his unger was kindled againſt Judah,</hi> verſ. 26. and verſ. 29.30. he went out to battell with <hi>Pharaoh Nechoh,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh Nechoh</hi> ſlew good King <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> oh what a ſtoppage was made in <hi>Iudas</hi> mercy? what is the matter? let us enquire into that, here are two cauſes; at the 26 <hi>verſ.</hi> you have mention made of <hi>Manaſſehs</hi> ſin, <hi>the Lord turned not from the fierceneſſe of his great wrath, wherewith his anger was kindled againſt Iudah, becauſe of all the provocations that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh had provoked him withall;</hi> the people were not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly humbled for their fathers ſins: and good King <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> goes up to war, and did not ſeek the Lord before as he ſhould have done. So that want of humiliation, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55139:12"/>flacking in the worke of prayer made this ſtop. On the contrary, you ſhall read a notable place, <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.21, 22, 23. when the Jews came out of <hi>Babilon</hi> to build the Temple, they were way-layd by their enemies, and in the midſt of the field <hi>Ezra</hi> proclaims a Faſt; a ſtrange kind of faſting and praying to be in the field, ſo it was then, in the field by the rivers ſide they go to faſting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: but <hi>Ezra</hi> might have had a guard from the King, why had he not? verſe 22. <hi>For I was aſhamed to aske of the King a band of Souldiers and horſemen, to helpe us againſt the enemy in the way, becauſe we had ſpoken unto the King, ſaying; The hand of our God is upon all them for good that ſeeke him, but his power and his wrath is against all them that forſake him: ſo we faſted and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought our God for this, and he was entreated of us.</hi> Marke, faſting and prayer was their convoy; oh beloved, what will not faſting and prayer do, when we are beſet with divers enemies? there muſt be theſe two, the ſlacking of theſe make a ſtop. As for prayer, firſt, you know how it was with the Iſraelites when they fought againſt <hi>Amalek,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> held up his hand, Iſrael prevailed, when he let fall his hand, <hi>Amalek</hi> prevailed; ſlacking in prayer made a ſtop. And ſo likewiſe for humiliation; there are two things that are oppoſite to that which makes a ſtop; ſpirituall pride, and alſo nice curioſity concerning the means of grace. Spirituall pride makes a ſtop. <hi>Paul</hi> was caught up into the third heaven, and had great reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; but leſt he ſhould be proud, and a ſtop ſhould be made in that mercy, a meſſenger of Sathan is ſent to buffet him. It is recorded of a Frenchman, having read excellent Lectures of Divinity, ſome of his auditors came to him, and deſired him that he would print them, he was ſo puffed up withall, as he broke out into this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy: Lord Jeſus, how art thou beholden to me? if I had turned my wits againſt thee, how much hurt could I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55139:12"/>have done thee? whereupon he was ſtricken with ſuch blindneſſe, ignorance, and dulneſſe, as he was two yeare after learning the Lords Prayer: this I ſpeake, to ſhew what a ſtoppage ſpirituall pride will make.</p>
            <p>And for curious niceneſſe about the means of grace, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. The Arke being in the hands and Countrey of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> they ſent it back, and ſo the Arke return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God was returning; but at the 19 <hi>verſe,</hi> the Lord ſmote of the people fifty thouſand threeſcore and ten men, why? becauſe they had looked into the Arke of the Lord; their fooliſh niceneſſe and curioſity about the Arke, what a ſtoppage it made in the way of mercy? It is recorded by Hiſtorians, that before the great maſſacre in France, the Proteſtants were grown ſo curious about preaching, that no preaching would down with them, but acute ſententious preaching. Beloved, both theſe are oppoſite to humiliation; and where theſe two, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation falls, and prayer ſlacks, there is a ſtoppage made, then will the Lord ſay to Mercy, ſtand, go no farther. For the preſent, God be thanked there is a day of humiliation, and a ſpirit of prayer up in the field, but when of late the enemies began to fall, how did men leave off prayer, and began to inſult over the enemies, the Lord ſaw this, and therefore a ſtoppage was made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy.</p>
            <p n="6">6. In the ſixt place. An unthankfull receiving of the mercies that God hath given us, and a ſlight beholding of the great works he hath done before us now lately, is another ſin that hath made a ſtoppage in our mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.7. It is ſayd concerning the Iſralites, <hi>Our fathers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not thy wonders in Egypt, they remembred not the multitude of thy mercies, but provoked him at the ſea, even the red ſea;</hi> there lyes the emphaſis at the ſea, even the red ſea that God carried them through. So you have a notable place for this purpoſe, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.14, 15. <hi>Give them a miſcarrying
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55139:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:55139:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:55139:14"/>wombe and dry breaſts,</hi> they ſhall conceive, mercy ſhall be begun, but it ſhall not bring forth, why? at the 15. ver. <hi>All their wickedneſſe is in Gilgal:</hi> why, how was all their wickedneſſe in <hi>Gilgal?</hi> they had much wickedneſſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: but the meaning is, <hi>Gilgal</hi> was the firſt place they came into when they went into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and there they were circumciſed, and there the Lord roaled away their reproach, and therfore it was called <hi>Gilgal;</hi> now to ſin in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> in that place where the Lord bad done ſo much for them, though they ſinned in other places, yet the ſin there was ſo great, as if all the ſin were there, becauſe that was a place of ſpeciall mercy; <hi>for there I hated them, for the wickedneſſe of their doings I will drive them out of mine houſe, I will love them no more;</hi> there is a ſtoppage made in mercy, when ſin is in <hi>Gilgal,</hi> in the place of ſuch and ſuch mercy. So my beloved, you all know what great things the Lord hath done for this place, you were brought exceeding low into great ſtraights, oh poor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted diſtreſſed <hi>England;</hi> but in the midſt of all your troubles and fears, the Lord created a Parliament for you, and delivered you with great deliverances; and if after all this you will go on in the way of ſin, and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly regard all that God hath done, this provokes God to make a ſtop. Marke how <hi>Ezra</hi> reaſons for this purpoſe, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. they had committed a great ſin in taking of the daughters of the Countrey to themſelves to wife, ver. 10. <hi>And now, oh our God, what ſhall we ſay after this? for we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken thy Commandements,</hi> Ez. 13. <hi>and after all that is come upon us for our evill deeds, and for our treſpaſſe; ſeeing that thou our God hast puniſhed us leſſe than our iniquities deſerve, and haſt given us ſuch deliverance as this:</hi> ſee where the emphaſis lyes, not deliverance only, but ſuch deliverance: <hi>ſhould we again breake thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and joyn in affinity with the people of theſe abominations? wouldſt thou not be angry with us, till thou hadſt confumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping?</hi> Now my beloved, you
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55139:14"/>ſee where he ſets the emphaſis, and truely have not we this word, (ſuch) written upon our deliverances; you were oppreſſed in your eſtates, and you are delivered from thoſe manifold oppreſſions; you were oppreſſed in your conſciences by the inventions of men, and you are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from thoſe heavy oppreſſions in a great meaſure; you were in great danger to have layn in bloud you and your children, and you were delivered from that bloody War with <hi>Scotland;</hi> and your Parliament worthies of late, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from a helliſh conſpiracie, I had almoſt ſaid as bad as that of the Powder-plot: and now I ſay after ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, if you will go on ſtill in the way of ſinning, how juſt is it with God to ſay, oh <hi>England,</hi> I thought to have don thee good, and to have built thee, but becauſe he that was a drunkard before, is a drunkard ſtill; he that was a ſwearer before, is a ſwearer ſtill; he that was a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath breaker before, a lyar, and unclean perſon before, is ſo ſtill; therefore I will now unkingdome thee, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>church thee, if after ſuch mercies and ſuch deliverances you ſhall go on in a way of ſin, I will make a ſtop in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and in all the good I thought to do; this hath made a ſtop in our <hi>Englands</hi> mercies.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The laſt ſin that makes a ſtop in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, is a worldly diſpoſition, whereby a man hangs back unto the great work of God, and the glorious reformation that is now a doing. You know that when they came out of <hi>Babilon</hi> and were to build the temple, the people were for their fieled houſes, and the temple went not on ſo long as they ſtack to their fieled houſes, but when once they were brought off from their fieled houſes, the temple was built, and they ſetled. So now the Lord is about to rebuild you, and build a temple among you; if our hearts be after our fieled houſes, how juſt is it with God to ſay, I thought to do you good, but you will not be at the coſt; I know you would have your brethren
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55139:15"/>in <hi>Ireland</hi> delivered, but you will not be at the coſt, you that are rich will not lend twenty, or thirty, or a hundred pounds towards it; I thought to have gon on and purged the whole Kingdom, but you will not be at the coſt, you would have the pictures out of your windowes, but you are loth to be at the coſt to buy new glaſſe; you would have Preaching Miniſters in every Congregation, but you are loth to be at the charge; this makes a ſtop in our <hi>Englands</hi> mercy. Thus I have to my poore abilty ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you the ſeven ſins that make a ſtop in the Lords pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of mercy; the Lord grant we may lay them to heart, and be humbled for them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> We grant theſe are the ſins that do make a ſtop in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, and the Lord is gone out of the way of mercy, and is angry; how ſhall we open a way to <hi>Englands</hi> mercy? how ſhall we bring God back againe? and how may the Lords anger be appeaſed?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> In anſwer to this, I ſhall ſhew you firſt it is a hard thing to appeaſe Gods anger when it is gone out.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It muſt be done, and that quickly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Shew you what you ſhall do that you may do it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt therefore; It is an exceeding hard thing and very difficult to appeaſe Gods anger. 1. Gods anger is compared to a ſtream; <hi>Tophet is prepared of old for the King</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>and out of his mouth goes a ſtream of fire.</hi> It is hard to turn a ſtream, you may eaſily turn the water when it is in the gutter before it comes into the ſtream, but when it is gotten into the river, it is hard turning of it; Gods wrath is a ſtreame, it is hard turning of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When you do ſolicite God to turn out of the way of his wrath, and turn into a way of mercy, you ſolicite him to that which is not for his eaſe, that is a burthen to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55139:15"/>him. Though you think you have great intereſt in a man, if you ſolicite him to that which is not for his eaſe, you will hardly obtain: now God ſayes in Scripture, it is an eaſe to him to be avenged on his adverſaries; ah, <hi>I will eaſe my ſelfe of my adverſaries:</hi> when you turn him from wrath, you turn him from eaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Again; there are but few to do it. If the ſea breaks over the bankes, and there are but few to ſtop it, it is hard to do; If fire hath taken two or three houſes in a ſtreet; and but few to quench it, it is hard to do: the fire of Gods anger is broken out, and there are but few to quench it; it is a hard thing therefore.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Again, God ſeems to be engaged in the way of his wrath. God walks according to his Word; now ſayes God, you would have me returne again to the way of my mercy, and leave off mine anger, and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you tell me you do pray, and humble your ſelves, and reform; but was it not ſo in <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> time? his heart melted, and he prayed, and broke down the images and pictures, and the offenders <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts were puniſhed; nevertheleſſe I turned not from the fierceneſſe of my wrath; why ſhould I turn from mine anger now for your ſakes, more than in <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> time? oh, it is a hard thing to turn God from his anger.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But it muſt be done, and done quickly; if a fire be broken out and not quenched quickly, it is more hard to quench: if the ſea breaks in at a place, and be not ſtopt quickly, it is more hard to ſtop. Run in and make an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement quickly, ſayes <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Aaron,</hi> it muſt be done quickly.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What then ſhall we do? do as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did: There are ſix things that <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did here, when they fled before the men of <hi>Ai.</hi> Firſt, he was very ſenſible of Gods ſtroke that was given to them; for he ſayes, Lord, would we had
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55139:16"/>been contented in the wilderneſſe. 2. He was humbled under Gods hand, for it is ſaid he rent his clothes, and fell down upon the earth. 3. And he prayed, and cryed mightily unto God, as you read in the chapter. 4. And he put away the evill of their doings. 5. And he puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Achan</hi> the offender. 6. He made an holy reſignation. And there muſt be a concurrence of all theſe ſix things, if we would bring God back into the way of his mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt be ſenſible of Gods ſtroke. Though men be greatly afflicted, yet if they be not ſenſible of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and of the ſtroak that God gives them, ſays God, I have ſpent one rod upon them, and they do not feel it, I will lay on till bloud come; God will make men ſenſible of their afflictions, and of the afflictions of the Church, elſe he layes on more.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, though a man be very ſenſible of Gods ſtroak and hand, yet notwithſtanding, if he be not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under the hand of the Lord, God will not exalt him; for ſayes the Lord, I have promiſed indeed, that if men humble themſelves under my mighty hand, they ſhall be exalted; and I have ſayd, if the people upon whom my name is called, humble themſelves, I will hear. He hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled himſelf much. This will mortifie your ſins as your ſins mortified and took captive your duties, and this muſt be don throughly, and to move us to it, 1. Take notice of the generall darknes that is in the land, how ſew know what they would have in a way of Reformation, what is agreeable to Gods way, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.10.11. The way to ſee ſtars in the day, is to go to the bottome of a well. But now here is a company are not humbled, what faſhion have they left ſince? wherein does it appear that you are more humbled? this muſt be; that is the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though that a man be humbled, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding if he does not pray, and cry mightily to God, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55139:16"/>cannot fetch God back againe, for ſayes God I am enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to my word, and I walk by rule; when I threatned <hi>Nineveh,</hi> the King went from his throne and went in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth and aſhes, and they cryed mightily unto me, and doe you thinke if you doe not cry mightily that I will returne in mercy to you? oh ſayes God I have given you more then <hi>Nineveh,</hi> you know more and you muſt doe more, they cryed mightily, and ſhall not you cry migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily? we muſt pray more then ordinary, ſo did <hi>Moſes,</hi> and for motives to it: 1. It is all that ſome of you can doe, you cannot help otherwayes by building God an houſe, lending money, &amp;c. but you may pray. 2. If you be idle you will envy thoſe that do pray; for it is a ſure rule, thoſe that ſtand by will envy the workmen, and what that will do, you may in <hi>Cain</hi> to <hi>Abel,</hi> when his ſacrifice was rejected. 3. The ſcales may ſeem to hang even, it may be your grain of prayer, may turn them to mercy. 4. The Lord ſeems to be going, he is riſing; when the Judge ſits ſtill, the malefactor does not lift up his voice and cry after him; but when the malefactor is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the Judge riſeth and goes off the bench, then the poore malefactor lifteth up his voice, and cries, good my Lord, good my Lord. So when God is riſing and going off the bench, ſhall not men cry, and cry mightily unto him, pray, and pray mightily unto him? Beloved, the Lord ſeems to be going off the bench, oh you that never prayed, now pray; you that have deſpiſed prayer, and praying meetings, now pray; you that have a heart to pray, pray now, &amp; cry mightily unto the Lord your God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though a man does pray, and cry mightily unto God, yet notwithſtanding if he does not turn from the evill of his doings, all is nothing; yet ſayes the Lord I am conſtant to my rule, and I have promiſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.9. <hi>If thou take away from the middeſt of thee the yoak, the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55139:17"/>forth of the ſinger &amp; ſpeaking vanity;</hi> if you put away the evill of your doings, what then? then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall anſwer preſently; thou ſhalt cry, and he anſwer ſenſibly, and ſay there am I. And ſo <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.14. they having come and cried to the Lord, the Lord gives them this anſwer, <hi>Go and cry unto the gods which you have choſen, let them deliver you in the time of your tribulation. And the children of Iſrael ſayd to the Lord, we have ſind, do thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us whatſoever ſeemeth good unto thee; deliver us only we pray thee this day: and they put away the ſtrange gods from among them, and feared the Lord:</hi> they cryed before, but now they prayed and put away their ſtrange Gods, <hi>and his ſoul was grieved for the miſery of Iſrael.</hi> So now will the Lord do, when people are ſenſible of his hand, and are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and cry, and cry much unto him, and put away the evill of their doings. this will prevaile. Wherefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved in the Lord, let us now joyn together in this work, and for the Lords ſake put away the evill of your doings. All you that heare me this day, are of three ſorts, either ſuch as do live upon your Lands: or ſuch as live upon your trades: or ſuch as live by keeping Taverns and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes. If you be ſuch as live upon your Lands, then thinke and ſay with your ſelves, I ſee there is a ſtoppage made in <hi>Englands</hi> mercy, come oh my ſoul, it may be it is my ſin hath done it; may be I have lived ſo much upon my Lands, as I have lived little or nothing upon Chriſt, I will learn to live more upon Chriſt, and leſſe upon my Lands. If you be ſuch as live upon your Trades, ſay, hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, wife, children, ſervants, it may be it is our ſin that hath made this ſtop, our lying, our falſe dealing, our breaking of the Sabbath, ſelling upon the Sabbath for gain, it may be it is our poor family that hath made the ſtop, let us put away the evill of our doings. If you be ſuch as keep Taverns and Alehouſes, ſay it may be it is the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55139:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55139:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55139:18"/>drunkenneſſe that I have ſuffered in my houſe, the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of oaths that are ſworn in my family, for my part I will never have <hi>Irelands</hi> blood lye at my door; therefore ſervants, children, friends, I charge you no more lying, no more ſwearing, no more Sabbath breaking, for the Lords ſake, and for our poor brethrens ſake in <hi>Ireland,</hi> let us put away the evill of our doings, you that have been drunkards, ſwearers, or adulterers, put away the evill of your doings, it may be this will bring God back again.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But though there be this, yet unleſſe the troubles of <hi>England,</hi> the Achans be brought forth to puniſhment and throwne over-board, the Sea cannot be appeaſed, the ſtorme will not down. For ſayes the Lord I am the ſame God that I was when wrath brake out upon Iſrael, then ſtood up <hi>Phineas</hi> and flow <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> and my wrath was ſtayed: when wrath broke out in <hi>Joſhuas</hi> time, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan</hi> was brought forth and puniſhed, and ſo my wrath was ſtayed: do you think that I will take leſſe at your hands? Therefore let us pray that the <hi>Achans</hi> may be brought forth, and when they are brought forth juſtifie the Worthies of the Lord, own them, guard them, and ſtand by them: And when the worke is done, rejoice with fear and trembling, waſh your feet in the blood of the wicked, and give glory to God, and ſay bleſſed be the Lord who only doth great things, marvelous are thy works Lord God Almighty, who would not fear thee?</p>
            <p n="6">6. He made an holy reſignation of himſelfe to be at Gods diſpoſing, ſo we may ſee <hi>Araunah</hi> did: 1. <hi>Ch:</hi> 21.23. <hi>Then Ornan ſaid to David take it to thee &amp;c.</hi> He gave up his Threſhing-floor and his Oxen, and his Threſhing inſtruments, thoſe things that were his livelyhood: ſo ſhould we offer up our ſhops, our trades, yea our ſelves and all we have to God.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55139:19"/>
            <p>Thus you have heard when God is in a way of mercy, ſin does make a ſtoppage in his proceedings, you acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge there is a ſtoppage made in our mercy: you have heard that thoſe ſinnes are as theeves in our candle that does ſmeare out our comforts: you have heard what a hard thing it is to bring God back to mercy again: you have heard the worke muſt be done: and you have heard what to do. Wherefore let every man as in the ſight of God goe home, and thinke, and ſay, and reſolve with himſelfe, I have not beene much affected with <hi>Irelands</hi> condition, I confeſſe it, the Lord forgive me, but I will look more into it then ever I have done, I have not been much humbled for my own ſin, and the ſins of the time, but the Lord pardon it, and I will be more humbled, I have not cryed unto the Lord, but from this day follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I will cry mightily unto the Lord my God, it may be he will returne: and I will put away the evill of my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, I have been an unclean perſon, I have been a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath breaker, and have been proud of this Coate and that gold lace, I will be proud no more, farwell all bad company: and I will pray that juſtice may be done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all <hi>Achans</hi> and Troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and when it is done I will rejoice with trembling. And thus I have done the firſt Doctrine, when God is in a way of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards his people, there ſin makes a ſtoppage in his proceedings.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55139:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:55139:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
